<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Anno xiiij. reginæ Elizabethe at the Parliament begunne and holden at Westminster the eyght of Maye, in the xiiij. yere of the raigne of our most gratious soueraigne lady Elizabeth, by the grace of God, of Englande, Fraunce and Ireland, queene, defendour of the fayth, &amp;c. and there continued vntyll the last of June folowyng, to the hygh pleasure of almightie God, and the weale publique of this realme, were enacted as foloweth.</title>
            <title>Laws, etc.</title>
            <author>England and Wales.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 112KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A23033</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22969608</idno>
  <idno type="VID">25991</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240893367</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 9477A.5</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S2002</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A23033)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25991)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1793:36)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Anno xiiij. reginæ Elizabethe at the Parliament begunne and holden at Westminster the eyght of Maye, in the xiiij. yere of the raigne of our most gratious soueraigne lady Elizabeth, by the grace of God, of Englande, Fraunce and Ireland, queene, defendour of the fayth, &amp;c. and there continued vntyll the last of June folowyng, to the hygh pleasure of almightie God, and the weale publique of this realme, were enacted as foloweth.</title>
                  <title>Laws, etc.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1558-1603 : Elizabeth I)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[46] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted at London in Powles Churchyarde by Richarde Iugge, printer to the Queenes Maiestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1572.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication and publisher from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁶ (last leaf blank).</note>
                  <note>Title within ornamental border.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Law --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25991:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25991:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno. xiiij. Reginae Elizabethe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶ <hi>At the parliament</hi> begunne and holden at Westminster the eyght of Maye, <hi>in the .xiiij. yere of the raigne of our most gratious soueraigne Lady Elizabeth, by the grace of God, of Englande, Fraunce, and Ireland Queene, defendour of the fayth. &amp;c.</hi> and there continued vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyll the last of Iune folowyng.</p>
            <p>To the hygh pleasure of almightie God, and the weale publique of this Realme, were enacted as fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>1572.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:25991:2"/>
            <head>The Table.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1 <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>N Acte for the punishment of suche as shall rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liously take or detayne, or conspire to take or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne from the Queenes Maiestie, anye of her castles, towres, fortresses, holdes. &amp;c.</item>
               <item>2 An Acte agaynst suche as shal conspire or practise the enlargement of any prisoner committed for high treason.</item>
               <item>3 An Acte agaynst the forgyng and counterfeytyng of forraigne coygne, beyng not currant within this Realme.</item>
               <item>4 An Acte to reuiue a statute made <hi>Anno primo</hi> of the Queenes Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties raigne, inhibiting the carying of leather, tallowe, &amp; raw hydes out of the Realme.</item>
               <item>5 An Acte for the punishment of vacaboundes, and for the releefe of the poore and impotent.</item>
               <item>6 An Acte for thexplanation of a statute made againste fugitiues ouer the seas, in the .xiii. yere of the Queenes Maiesties raigne.</item>
               <item>7 An Acte agaynst the deceiptes of vnder Collectours of the tenthes and subsedies of the Cleargie.</item>
               <item>8 An Acte for the auoydyng of recoueries suffred by collusion by tenantes for terme of lyfe, and suche others.</item>
               <item>9 An Acte declaryng that the tenaunt and defendaunt, may haue a <hi>tales de circumstantibus,</hi> aswel as the demaundant or playntife.</item>
               <item>10 An Acte to refourme the excessiue length of Carseyes.</item>
               <item>11 An Acte for the continuation, explanation, perfityng, and enlargyng of diuers statutes.</item>
               <item>12 An Acte for the repeale of a statute made <hi>Anno. viii.</hi> of the Queenes Maiesties raigne, touching the Towne of Shrewesburie.</item>
               <item>13 An Acte for the annexing of Hexham and Hexham Shire to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Northumberlande.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:25991:2"/>
            <head>❧ An Act for the punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of such as shal rebelliously take or detayne, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spire to take or detayne from the Queenes Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie, any of her Castles, Towres, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tresses, holdes. &amp;c. Chapter. j.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR the better auoydyng of</hi> all suche vnlawfull practises, se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete conspiracies, and deuises, as lately haue benne stirred and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by some euil disposed persons, agaynst our most gratious So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne Lady the Queene, in seekyng by false conspiracies, and vndue meanes, to surprise and take from her Maiestie some of her Castles, Towres, Fortresses, Shippes, Ordinaunces, Artylla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and other munitions of warre: be it enacted by the Queenes most excellent Maiestie, with thassent of the Lordes Spirituall and Temporall, and the Commons in this present Parliament assembled, and by thaucthoritie of the same, that if any person or persons whatsoeuer, at anye tyme hereafter do within this Realme, or els where, vnlawfully, &amp; of his or their owne auctho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie compasse, imagine, conspire, practise, or deuise, by any wayes or meanes, with force, or by any craft, deuice, or sleight, malitious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and rebelliously, to take, or to deteyne, or keepe from our sayde Soueraigne Lady the Queene, any of her Castles, Towres, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tresses, or holdes, or malitiously and rebelliously to rase, burne, or destroy any Castle, Bulwercke, or forte, or any part of them, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng anye munition or ordinaunce of the Queenes Maiesties therein, or appoynted to be garded with any souldiers for defence thereof within this Realme, or within any of her Maiesties do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions or countreys, or the marches of the same, and the same compasses, imaginations, practises, conspiracies, or deuises, or any of them, shal, and do aduisedly by any expresse wordes, speach, act, deede, or wryting, expresse, vtter, or declare, for any the maliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and rebellious intentes aforesayde: that then euery such per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
<pb facs="tcp:25991:3"/> and persons, so hereafter offendyng in anye the premisses, their aydours, counsellours, cōforters, consentours, &amp; abettours, knowyng thereof, beyng thereof lawfully conuicted accordyng to the lawes of this Realme, shalbe iudged a felon, and felons, and that euery suche offence shalbe iudged to be felonie, &amp; the offender &amp; offendours therin, their said aydours, comforters, counsellours, and abettours, beyng therof lawfully conuicted, shal haue &amp; suffer paynes of death, as in cases of felonie, without hauyng any be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite of cleargie or sanctuarie, and also shal forfayte and lose all his goodes and cattels, landes and tenementes, as in other cases of felonie hath ben vsed and accustomed.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by thaucthoritie aforesayde, that if any person or persons, do at any tyme hereafter with force, mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiously and rebelliously detayne, keepe, or withholde, from the Queenes Maiestie, any of her Castles, Towres, Fortresses, or holdes, within this Realme, or within any her Maiesties domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions or Countreys, or Marches of the same: or do malitiously, rebelliously, and with force detayne, keepe, or withholde from her Maiestie, any of her Shippes, Ordinaunce, Artyllarie, or other munitions, or fortifications of warres, &amp; do not render and geue vp the same to our sayde soueraigne Lady, or to suche person as her Maiestie shal appoynt to receaue the same to her Maiesties vse, within sixe dayes next after he or they so offendyng, shalbe commaunded by our sayde soueraigne Lady the Queene; by open proclamations vnder the great Seale of Englande, to be made in any place or market Towne within the Countie where any such offence shalbe committed: or shal wylfully, malitiously, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belliously, burne or destroy, or cause to be burned or destroyed, any of the Queenes shippes: or malitiously, &amp; rebelliously barre, or cause to be barred, any hauen within any of the Queenes Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties dominions: that then euery suche person and persons so of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendyng, their aydours, counsellours, &amp; abettours, beyng thereof lawfully conuict, accordyng to the lawes of this Realme, shalbe adiudged traytours, and their offences in any the premisses, shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be accepted, iudged, and taken for hygh treason, &amp; the offendours therin, their aydours, counsellours, and abettours, beyng thereof lawfully conuict according to the lawes of this Realme, shal haue and suffer suche paynes of death, and also shal forfayte and lose, as in cases of hygh treason is limited and accustomed. This acte to endure duryng the Queenes Maiesties lyfe that nowe is, onely.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:25991:3"/>
            <head>❧ An Acte agaynst suche as shal conspire or practise the enlargement of any priso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, committed for hygh treason. Chapter. ij.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Orasmuch as great daunger</hi> may ensue to the Queenes Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties person, and great trouble to the state of the Realme, by vnlawfull conspiracies, deuises, and imaginatiōs, to enlarge and set at libertie such persons, as be, or shalbe committed to anye pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, garde, or custodie, for anye treason touchyng the royall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of our saide soueraigne Lady, agaynst whiche deuises, conspira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and imaginations, sufficient remedie by the lawes of this Realme, hath not ben heretofore had, ne prouided, vnlesse the same conspiracies, imaginations, and deuices, were executed and brought to effect: Be it therefore enacted by our sayde soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lady the Queene, the Lordes Spiritual and Temporal, and the Commons in this Parliament assembled, and by the aucthoritie of the same, that if anye person or persons, at anye tyme after the ende of this present session of Parliament, shall imagine, conspire, deuise, inuent, or goe about vnlawfully and malitiously, to enlarge, or set at libertie, anye person or persons, committed, or to be committed to any prison, garde, or custodie, by her hyghnesse especial commaundement for any treason, or suspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of treason, concernyng the person of our sayde soueraigne Lady y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Queene, before any inditement of such person, so sought or intended to be set at large, or libertie, as is aforesayde, and the same conspiracies, imaginations, deuises, or inuentions, shal by expresse wordes, wrytyng, or other matter, or acte, expressely, or manifestly, set foorth, vtter, or declare: that then euery person so offendyng, shal incurre the penaltie and forfayture of misprision of treason, and that all and euery offence and offences to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted and donne, as is aforesayde, shalbe deemed and taken for
<pb facs="tcp:25991:4"/> misprision of Treason.</p>
            <p>And be it also enacted by the aucthoritie aforesayde, that if any person or persons, at any tyme after thende of this present session of Parliament, shal imagine, conspire, deuise, inuent, or go about vnlawfully and malitiously, to enlarge, or set at libertie, any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son or persons, committed, or to be committed to any prison, gard, or custodie, beyng, or whiche hereafter shalbe indicted of any trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, in any wyse concernyng the person of our sayde soueraigne Lady the Queene, and the same conspiracies, imaginations, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uises, or inuentions, shall by expresse wordes, writing, or other matter, or acte, expressely or manifestly, set foorth, vtter, or declare: that then euery suche person so offendyng, shalbe deemed and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudged a felon, and suffer, lose, and forfayte, as in cases of felonie, by the dewe course of the lawes of this Realme.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by thaucthoritie aforesayde, that if any person or persons, at any tyme after thende of this present session of Parliament, shal imagine, conspire, deuise, inuent, or go about vnlawfully and malitiously to enlarge, or set at libertie any person or persons, beyng committed to any prison, garde, or custodie, after the same person or persons, is, or shalbe attaynted or conuicted of any treason, in any wyse concernyng the royall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of our sayde Soueraigne Lady the Queene, and the same conspiracies, imaginations, deuises, or inuentions, shall by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse wordes, writyng, matter, or acte, as is aforesayde, set foorth, vtter, or declare: that then euery suche person so offendyng, shalbe deemed, and adiudged an hygh traytour, and shall suffer, lose, and forfayte, as in cases of hygh treason by the lawes and statutes of this Realme. This act to endure duryng the Queenes Maiesties lyfe, that nowe is, onely.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:25991:4"/>
            <head>❧ An Act agaynst the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging and counterfeyting of forraigne coygne, beyng not currant within this Realme. Chapter. iij.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Orasmuch as by the lawes or</hi> statutes of this Realme, small or no condigne punishment is at this tyme prouided for suche euyll disposed persons, as shall coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfayte, or forge suche kynde of golde or syluer of other Realmes, as is not the proper coygne of this Realme, nor currant in payment within this Realme: by reason whereof, diuers euyll disposed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, aswel without this Realme, as within, are encouraged and boldened dayly to counterfayte or forge suche kynde of golde and siluer, and vtter the same in this Realme, in great disceyt of her Maiesties subiectes, Be it enacted by our sayde soueraigne Lady the Queene, the lordes Spirituall and Temporall, and the Commons of this present Parliament assembled, and by thaucthoritie of the same, that if anye person or persons, hereafter falsely forge or counterfayte any suche kynde of coygne of gold or syluer, as is not y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> proper coygne of this Realme, nor permitted to be currant within this Realme: that then euery suche offence shalbe deemed and iudged misprision of hygh trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, and the offendours therein, their procurers, aydours, and abettours, beyng conuict accordyng to the lawes of this Realme of suche offences, shalbe imsprisoned, and forfayte suche landes, goodes, and chattelles, as in cases of misprision of treason, for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceilment of hygh treason.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:25991:5"/>
            <head>An acte to reuiue a statute made Anno primo of the Queenes Maiesties raigne, inhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting the carying of leather, tallowe, and rawe hides out of the Realme. Chapter. iiij.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here in the Parliament begunne at</hi> Westminster the .xxiii. day of Ianuary, in the first yere of the raigne of our soueraigne La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Queenes most excellent Maiestie, there was one very good act &amp; statute made, prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bityng the transportyng and carying of lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, rawe hydes, and tallowe out of this Realme, entituled, An act, that the conuey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of leather, tallowe, or rawe hydes out of the Realme for mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaundise, shalbe felonie: whiche acte and statute was made to continue but for a certayne tyme, and nowe is expired and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined for want of continuaunce at the last Parliament. And for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asmuche as by experience it hath well appeared, that since the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination of the sayde good lawe and statute, there hath ben, and yet dayly is such great transportation of leather, rawe hides, &amp; tallowe out of this Realme, that thereby great scarsitie &amp; dearth thereof is nowe growen amonges the Queenes Maiesties most louing and obedient subiectes, and specially amonges those of the poorest sorte, who are nowe compelled to pay for their bootes and shoes almost double the prise that they dyd before the determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the sayde good lawe and statute. For remedie wherof, be it enacted by the Queenes most excellent Maiestie, with thassent of the lordes spiritual and temporall, &amp; the commons in this present Parliament assembled, and by the aucthoritie of the same, that the sayde acte and statute made in the sayd Parliament, begunne the sayd xxiii. day of Ianuarie, in the sayde first yere, entituled as is beforesayde, and al and euery braunche, article, clause, and sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence therein conteyned, shall from and after the feast day of saint Bartholomewe thapostle next comming, be reuyued, and stande and be in ful force and effect, for, and duryng the space of .vii. yeres then next folowyng, and also after the ende of the sayde .vii. yeres, then to thend of the next Parliament, next folowyng the end and determination of the sayde .vii. yeres, any thyng heretofore had, made, or done, or suffered to the cōtrary therof, notwithstandyng.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:25991:5"/>
            <head>❧ An Act for the punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of vacabondes, and for the releefe of the poore and impotent. Chapter. v.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here all the partes of this</hi> Realme of Englande and Wales, be presently with roges, vacabon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, &amp; sturdie beggers exceedingly pestred, by meanes whereof dayly happeneth in the same Realme horrible murders, theftes, &amp; other great outrages, to the hygh dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleasure of almyghtie God, and to the great anoy of the common weale: and for auoydyng confusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by reason of nūbers of lawes, concernyng the premisses, standyng in force togeather: be it enac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that the statute made in the .xxii. yere of the raigne of the late kyng Henry the eyght, intituled, An acte concernyng aged, poore and impotent persons, compelled to lyue by almes, howe they shalbe ordered, and how vacabondes and myghtie strong beggers shalbe punished: &amp; one other acte, intituled, An acte touchyng the punishment of vacabonds, &amp; other idle persons, made in the third and fourth yeres of the raigne of the late king Edwarde the sixth: and one other acte made in the fifth yere of the raigne of our soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lady the Queenes Maiestie that nowe is, intituled, An acte for the releefe of the poore, and euery branche, article, clause, and sentence in them, and euery of them conteyned, shalbe from and after the feast of Saint Bartholomewe thapostle next com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng, vtterly voyde, frustrate, and of none effect.</p>
            <p>Be it also enacted by thauctoritie of this present parliamēt, as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel for the vtter suppressing of the said outragious enimies to the common weale, as for the charitable releeuing of the aged &amp; impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent poore people, in maner &amp; fourme folowyng. First, that al and euery person &amp; persons, whatsoeuer they be, beyng aboue the age of .xiiii. yeres, beyng hereafter set foorth by this act of parliament to be roges, vacabondes, or sturdie beggers, and be at any time af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the feast of Saint Bartholomewe the apostle next commyng
<pb facs="tcp:25991:6"/> taken beggyng in any parte of this Realme, or taken vagrants wandryng, and misordering themselues contrary to the purport of this present Acte of parliament, in any parte of the same, shal vpon their apprehencion, be brought before one of the Iustices of the peace, or Maior, or cheefe Officer of Cities, Boroughes, and Townes corporate, within the Countie, Citie, Boroughe, or Towne corporate where the apprehencion shal happen to be, and by the sayd Iustice or head officer to be presently committed to the common gaole of the sayde Countie, beyng apprehended within the Countie, or els suche other place as by the Iustices of peace of that Countie, or three of them, at any their generall Sessions shalbe appoynted: and if he be taken within any Citie, Borough, or Towne corporate, then to be cōmitted to the prison of the saide Citie, Borough, or Towne corporate, there to remayne without bayle or maynprise vntyll the next Sessions of the peace, or gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral gaole deliuerie for the said Shiere, Citie, Borough, or Towne corporate, to be holden, whiche shal firste happen: and the Consta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, or other officers, for the conueying of suche roge or vaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonde by commaundement of the sayde Iustices, to haue suche reasonable charges for them selues and the prisoner, from tyme to time, borne by the parish or parishes where the sayd roge or va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gabond shal happen to be takē, as to the discretion of the Iustices of peace present at the next assises, or at the Sessions of the peace then next kept, within the limit where the prisoner is apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, shal seeme conuenient. At which Sessions or gaole deliuerie, if suche person or persons be duely conuict of his or her rogishe or vacabondes trade of lyfe eyther by in quest of Officer, or by the testimonie of two honest and credible witnesses vpon their othes: that then immediatly he or she shalbe adiudged to be greeuously whipped, and burnt through the gristle of the ryght eare, with a hot iron of the compasse of an inche about, manifestyng his or her rogyshe kinde of lyfe, and his or her punishment receiued for the same, whereof entrie shalbe made of Recorde by the Clarcke of the peace of the same Shiere, in the recordes of the same Sessions, whiche iudgement shal also presently be executed, except some ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest person, valued at the last subsidie next before that tyme to fyue poundes in goodes, or twentie shillynges in landes, or els some such honest housholder, as by the Iustices of the peace of the same Countie, or two of them shalbe allowed, wyl of his charitie be contented presently to take such offendour before the same Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stices into his seruice for one whole yere next folowyng, and to that ende, wyll presently before the sayde Iustices, enter into band by recognisaunce to thuse of our Soueraigne Lady the Queene,
<pb facs="tcp:25991:6"/> to pay to our sayde soueraigne Lady, the summe of fyue poundes, if he keepeth not the sayde offendour in his seruice by the space of the sayde whole yere, and to bring hym or her vnto the sessions at the yeeres ende, or then good proofe of his or her death duryng the sayde yere, the sayde Clarcke of the peace, takyng for the sayde recognisaunce but .xii. d. onely. And if suche roge or vacabounde so taken into seruice, depart within the sayde yere from the sayde seruice, agaynst the wyl of hym that so taketh hym or her into ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice: that then such roge or vacabounde, shalbe whypped &amp; burnt through y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> gristle of the right eare with a hot iron, as is aforesaid.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes neuerthelesse, that yf the sayde person so committed, or to be committed, come before the next sessions of the peace, or the next gaole deliuerie to be holden for the sayde Countie, or before their committyng, and do fynde any suche suretie as is next before recited, to be bounde in fourme aforesaid, for hym or her for one whole yere: then the sayde person shal not tarrie in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> gaole til the next sessions, or til the next gaole deliuerie.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted, that the sayde person or persons so marked or adiudged to be burnt, as aforesayde, shall not be dealt withal againe by way of punishmēt by the space of fourtie dayes next after the sayde punishment executed, or adiudged to be burnt as is aforesayde, yf he or she haue license for the sayde fourtie dayes from two Iustices of the peace of the same Shire, testify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the punishment receaued, or iudgement geuen: but if after the sayde punishment executed, or iudgement geuen, the sayde person or persons so marked or hauyng receaued suche iudgement, do af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter threescore dayes next after he, she, or they, shall so be marked, eyther in the same Countie where he or she was so marked, or ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng receaued such iudgement, or els in any other Countie with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the sayde Realme of Englande or Wales, beyng of the age of eyghteene yeeres or aboue, do eftsones fal agayne to any kynde of rogishe or vacaboundes trade of lyfe: that then the sayde roge, vacabounde, or sturdie begger, from thencefoorth to be taken, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudged and deemed in all respectes as a felon, and shall in all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees receaue, haue, suffer, and forfayte as a felon, except some ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest person valued at the last Subsidie next before that tyme to tenne poundes in goodes, or fourtie shyllynges in landes, or els some suche honest housholder, as by the Iustices of the peace of the same Countie, or two of them shalbe allowed, of mere charitie wyll be contented before suche Iustices, as the sayde vacabounde is or shalbe arraigned of felonie, to take him or her into his seruice
<pb facs="tcp:25991:7"/> for two whole yeres then next folowing, and then before the same Iustices, wyll then presently put in bonde by recognisaunce of tenne poundes, to be leuyed of his landes, tenementes, goodes, and cattelles, to thuse of our sayde soueraigne Lady, yf he keepeth not the sayde offendour in his seruice for two whole yeres, and bryng him or her vnto the sessions at the sayde two yeres ende, or good proofe of his or her death. And if such roge or vacabounde so taken into seruice, depart within the same two yeres from his or her sayde seruice, agaynst the wyll of hym that so tooke hym or her into seruice: that then suche roge or vacabounde, shalbe taken, adiudged, and deemed, as a felon in all respectes, and shall in all degrees, haue, suffer, and forfayte as a felon, without allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce or benefite of Cleargie or Sanctuarie. And if suche roge or vacabounde, after fourtie dayes next after he or she shalbe two seuerall tymes taken into seruice, as is aforesayde, do eyther in the sayde Countie, or els where eftsones the thirde tyme fall agayne to a kynde of rogishe or vacabounde trade of lyfe: that then suche roge or vacabounde shalbe adiuded and deemed for a felon, and suffer paynes of death, and losse of landes and goodes as a felon, without allowaunce or benefite of Cleargie or Sanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuarie.</p>
            <p>And for the full expessyng, what person and persons shalbe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended within this braunche to be roges, vacaboundes, and sturdie beggers, to haue and receaue the punishment afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayde, for the sayde lewde maner of lyfe: it is nowe published, declared, and set foorth by the aucthoritie of this present Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, that all and euery suche person and persons, that be or vtter themselues to be Proctours or Procuratours, goyng in or about anye Countrey or Countreys within this Realme, without sufficient aucthoritie, deryued from, or vnder our soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lady the Queene: and all other idle persons goyng a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout in any Countrey of the sayde Realme, vsyng subtyll, craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and vnlawfull games or playes, and some of them faynyng them selues to haue knowledge in Phisnomie, Palmestrie, or other abused sciences, whereby they beare the people in hande they can tell their destenies, deathes, and fortunes, and suche other lyke fantasticall imaginations: and all and euery person and persons, beyng whole and myghtie in body, and able to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, hauyng not lande or maister, nor vsyng any lawfull mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaundize, craft, or mysterie, whereby he or she myght get his or her lyuyng, and can geue no reckenyng howe he or she doth law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb facs="tcp:25991:7"/> get his or her liuing: &amp; al fencers, bearewards, common play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in enterludes, &amp; mynstrels, not belongyng to any Baron of this Realme, or towards any other honorable personage of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter degree, al iuglers, pedlers, tinkers &amp; petie chapmen, which said fencers, bearewardes, common players in enterludes, minstrels, iuglers, pedlers, tynkers, &amp; petie chapmen, shal wander abroade, and haue not licence of two Iustices of the peace at the leaste, wherof one to be of the <hi>Quorum,</hi> where and in what Shire they shal happen to wander: and al common labourers, being persons able in bodye, vsyng loyteryng, and refusyng to worke for suche reasonable wages as is taxed, and commonly geuen, in suche partes where suche persons do or shal happen to dwel: and all counterfeytures of licences, passeportes, and al vsers of the same, knowyng the same to be counterfeyte: and al scollers of the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersities of Oxforde or Cambridge, that go about beggyng, not beyng aucthorised vnder the Seale of the sayde Vniuersities, by the Commissarie, Chauncelour, or vice Chauncelour of the same: and al shippemen, pretendyng losses by Sea, other then suche as shalbe herafter prouided for: and al persons deliuered out of gaoles, that begge for theyr fees, or do trauayle to theyr Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treyes or freendes, not hauyng licence from two Iustices of the peace of the same Countie where he or she was delyuered: shalbe taken, adiudged, and deemed roges, vacaboundes, and sturdie beggers, intended of by this present acte, together with al and euery suche other person and persons, as shalbe hereafter for alteryng and breaking of suche good orders as in the seconde part of this presente acte shalbe established for the releefe of the aged and impotent poore people, set foorth and declared to be vaca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundes.</p>
            <p>And further be it enacted, that yf any person or persons, after the sayde feast of saint Bartholomewe, geue anye harborough, money, or lodgyng, or any other releefe to any roge, vacabounde, or sturdie begger, eyther marked as before, or not marked, not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng suche a licence, as is before recited, from two Iustices of the peace then in continuance, and that duely prooued before the Iustices of the peace at theyr quarter sessions: shall make suche fine to the Queenes Maiestie, as by the discretions of the sayde Iustices, or the more part of them, at theyr general sessions shalbe assessed, so as the same exceede not twentie shyllynges. And also yf any person or persons do disturbe or let the execution of this act in any maner of wise, or make rescusse against any Maior, She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffe, Bayliffe, or other person, that shal endeuour hym selfe, for, or about the due execution hereof, shal forfeite &amp; lose fiue poundes,
<pb facs="tcp:25991:8"/> and ouer that, shal haue imprisonment at the Queenes Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties pleasure.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, that this acte, nor any thyng herein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned, shal extende to make any person or persons accessarie, or accessaries to the sayde felonies made by this statute, nor that any attainder by any the fellonies aforesayd, shal worke or be any corruption of blood in the issues or lyne of the person attainted.</p>
            <p>Prouided also, that it shalbe styl lawful to al maisters and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours of the Hospitalles, to lodge or harbour anye impotent or aged person or persons of charitie, or almes, accordyng to theyr foundation, and to geue money in almes, in as large maner as they are bounde to do by theyr foundation, to any suche aged or impotent person: any thyng herein conteyned to the contrary in any wyse, notwithstandyng.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, that shipmen, and souldiers, hauing licence of the next two Iustices of the peace to the place where they first happened to lande, or where they firste entred into this Realme, shal and may passe accordyng to the purporte of theyr licence, and intent of this acte of parliament: any thyng herein conteyned to the contrary in any wise, notwithstandyng.</p>
            <p>Be it also further prouided, that no licence recited in this sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, shall geue anye maner libertie, or be of any maner force, but only in the Shire whereof the graunter or graunters of suche li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence shalbe Iustice or Iustices of peace. Wherfore yf the sayd par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie licenced, wil haue any further passage without the daunger of this lawe, then the Shire where his first licence is graunted, it shalbe behoueful for him to procure and get in euery other Shire where he entendeth to passe, one other licence from two Iustices of the peace of the sayde Shire, and so from Shire to Shire, to the ende of his iourney. Be it also prouided, that this act, nor any thing therein conteyned, do in any wyse extende to any Cockers, or haruest folkes, that trauaile into any Countrey of this realme for haruest worke, eyther corne haruest, or hay haruest, yf they do worke and labour accordingly, neyther yet to any that happeneth to be robbed or spoyled by the way, neither yet to any seruing men that be of honest behauiour, that be turned from their maisters, or whose maister or maistresse shalbe dead, for the space of fire mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nethes next after suche turnyng away, or death of such maister or maistresse, so as euery such seruyng man hath a testimonial from his maister or maistresse, or from two Iustices of the peace of the same Countie, declaryng suche turnyng away, or suche death of his maister or maistresse.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, that it shalbe lawful to the lord Chaunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour
<pb facs="tcp:25991:8"/> or lorde Keper of the great seale of Englande for the tyme be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to make licence vnder the sayde great Seale, as heretofore hath benne accustomed, and that the sayde licence and licences, shall as largely extende as the contentes of them wyl beare: any thyng herein to the contrary in any wyse, notwithstandyng.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, and be it further enacted by the aucthori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie aforesayde, that this present acte, or any thyng therein contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, shall not extende to make frustrate or voyde any salfe condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>icte, passeporte, or licence, made and graunted, or to be made and graunted by the Lorde Deputie of Irelande, or by the Lorde go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour of the Townes and Garisons of Barwyke, or Carlisle, for the tyme beyng, or any other chiefe captayne or gouernour of any Castle or Fortresse of the Queenes Maiesties, or by any other in his or their absence hauyng the charge of the sayde Townes and Garisons, or by any the Guardians of the three Marches to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes Scotlande, or by any Generall, Lieuetenaunt, or other chiefe officer appoynted by the Queenes Maiestie to haue the charge and conduction of any Armie, Garison, or power of men, leuied or to be leuied by her hyghnesse order and appoyntment, and for the special seruice and affayres of her Maiestie, her heyres or successours, or by any priuate captayne vppon the dispersing of any armie, only to any souldiour or souldiours, or any other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son or persons what so euer, within this her Realmes of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande and Irelande, passing by vertue thereof about his or theyr lawfull businesse and affayres: but that he or they shall and may quietly without any let or disturbance, enioy the benefite, effect, and true meanyng thereof, in as large and ample manner and fourme, as heretofore it hath ben vsed and accustomed: any thyng in this present acte mentioned to the contrary in any wyse, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstandyng.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, that this present acte, or any thyng there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in conteyned, shall not in any wyse extende to the punishment of any suche person or persons, as by this statute are limitted for Roges, vnlesse the same be of the age of fourteene yeeres or aboue, but that they and euery of them vnder that age, shalbe punished with whipping or stockyng, as heretofore hath ben vsed and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted by the lawes and statutes in that case prouided, &amp; nowe repealed: this acte or any thyng therein conteyned to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hereof in any wyse, notwithstandyng.</p>
            <p>And it is further enacted by the aucthoritie aforesayde, that yf within any Towne or Parishe, where any suche vacabounde or roge shall happen to begge, or make his abode, contrary to the
<pb facs="tcp:25991:9"/> fourme of this statute, yf the Constable or Tything men be negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, and do not his or their best endeuour for the apprehension of suche vacabounde or roge, whiche there shall begge or make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode, contrary to the fourme in this statute limitted, or shall wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyngly suffer the saide vacabounde or roge to escape from the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment or order in this statute prescribed: that then the sayde Constable or Tything man in whom suche default shalbe, shall lose and forfaite for euery suche vacabounde and vagrant person, that shalbe suffered to begge, or make abode within his aucthori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, contrary to the fourme of this statute .vi. s. viii. d. And for as muche as charitie woulde, that poore, aged, and impotent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons shoulde as necessaryly be prouided for, as the sayde roges, va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caboundes, and sturdy beggers repressed, and that the sayde aged, impotent, and poore people should haue conuenient habitations and abydyng places throughout this realme to settle them selues vppon, to the ende that they, nor any of them shoulde hereafter begge, or wander about: It is therefore enacted by the aucthori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of this present Parliament, that the Iustices of peace of al and singuler the shyres of Englande and Wales, within the limittes of their commissions, and al other Iustices of the peace, Maiors, Sheriffes, Bayliffes, and other officers of al and euery Citie, Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough, Ridyng, and Franchesies within this Realme, whereof they be Iustices at peace within the limittes of their aucthoritie, shal at, or before the sayde feast of Saint Bartholomewe nexte comming, diuide them selues, and so beyng diuided, shall within euery of their seuerall diuisions and aucthorities, make diligent searche and enquirie of all aged, poore, impotent, and decayed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, borne within their sayde diuisions and limittes, or whiche were there dwellyng within three yeeres next before this present Parliament, whiche liue, or of necessitie be compelled to liue by almes of the charitie of the people, that be or shalbe abiding with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the limittes of their commissions and aucthorities: and shall vpon that searche made, make a register booke, conteynyng the names &amp; surnames of al such aged, decayed, and impotent poore people, as be within their sayde limittes and aucthorities, which shall alwayes remayne with the sayde Iustices, Maiors, Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liffes, or other head officers, or any one of them. And when the number of the sayde poore people forced to liue vppon almes, be by that meanes truely knowen, then the sayd Iustices, Maiors, Sheriffes, Bayliffes and other officers, shall within like conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient tyme, deuise and appoynt within euery theyr sayde seuerall diuisions, meete and conuenient places by their discretions, to
<pb facs="tcp:25991:9"/> settle the same poore people for their habitations and abidinges, yf the parishe within the whiche they shalbe founde, shall not, or wyl not prouide for them, and shall also within lyke conuenient tyme, number all the sayde poore people within theyr sayde seue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall limittes: and therevpon (hauyng regarde to the number) set downe what portion the weekely charge towards the reliefe and sustentation of the sayde poore people wyl amount vnto, within euery their sayde seueral diuisions and limittes: and that donne, they the sayde Iustices, Maiors, Sheriffes, Bayliffes, and other officers, within euery their seuerall commissions, aucthorities, diuisions, and limittes, shal by their good discretions taxe and as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sesse all and euery the inhabitauntes dwelling in al and euery Citie, Borough, Towne, Village, Hamlet, and place knowen within the sayde limittes and diuisions, to suche weekely charge, as they and euery of them shall weekely contribute towardes the releefe of the sayde poore people: and the names of all suche inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitauntes taxed, shall also enter into the sayde register booke to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather with their taxation: and also shall by their discretion, within euery their sayde diuisions and limittes, appoynt or see Collectours for one whole yeere to be appoynted of the sayde weekely portion, whiche shall collect &amp; geather the sayd proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and make deliuerie of so muche thereof, accordyng to the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion of the sayde Iustices, Maiors, Sheriffes, Bayliffes, and other officers to the sayde poore people, as the saide Iustices, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iors, Sheriffes, Bayliffes, and other officers shall appoynt them: And also shall appoynt ouerseers of the saide poore people by their discretions, to continue also for one whole yeere: and yf they doo refuse to be ouerseers, then euery of them so refusing, to forfayte tenne shillinges for euery suche default.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the aucthoritie aforesayde, that the Maior of the Citie of London, and the Maiors, Sheriffes, Bayliffes, and other head officers of euery other Citie, Borough, or Towne corporate, or his or theyr sufficient deputie or deputies within their Cities, Boroughes, and Townes corporate, and the Constables or Tything men of all and euery Hundred, Rape, and Wapencake, within all and euery the sayde shyres in Englande and Wales, in al and euery suche abydyng place and places with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in theyr hundredes, limittes, and precinctes, as shalbe appoynted to settle the poore people in, shal once euery moneth next after the
<pb facs="tcp:25991:10"/> sayde places so appoynted be inhabited with the sayde poore peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, accordyng to the intent of this present acte of Parliament, make a viewe and searche of al the aged, impotent, and lame per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons within the precinct of their iurisdictions: and all suche per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son and persons as they shall finde not beyng borne within that diuision, nor within the saide Cities, Boroughes, or Townes cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate, then shal they presently see the same poore people not there borne, nor dwellyng within the sayd three yeeres (except leprous people, and beddred people) to be conueyed on horsebacke, in carte, or otherwyse, as shall seeme best to their discretions, to the next Constable, and so from Constable to Constable the directest way, till the sayde person and persons be brought to the place where he or she was borne, or moste conuersaunt by the space of three yeeres next before, and there to be put in the abiding place, or one of the abydyng places in that Countrey appoynted, or to be appoynted for the habitation of the poore people of that coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, there to be prouided, kept, and nourished of almes, as is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresayde, vpon payne of twentie shillinges euery the sayde officer that neglecting.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the aucthoritie aforesayde, that yf any of the sayde poore people, vpon the appoyntment of the sayde Iustices or other officers, refuse to be bestowed in any of the sayde abydyng places before mentioned, but couet stil to holde on their trade of begging: or after they be once bestowed in the sayde aby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng place or places, doo depart and begge: then the sayde person and persons so offending, for the first offence to be accompted a roge or vacabounde, and to suffer as a roge or vacabounde in the first degree of pounishment set foorth by this acte, in all poyntes: And yf he, she, or they doo the seconde tyme offend, then to be este<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med as a roge or vacabound, and to suffer as a roge or vacabound in the last degree of pounishment set foorth by this acte, in all poyntes.</p>
            <p>And it is further enacted by aucthoritie of this present Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, that yf any manner of person or persons appoynted and elected to be Collectours, as is aforesayde, shall refuse the sayde of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, or shall after he hath agreed to it neglect the same, he shall forfaite and lose for euery offence to the vse of the poore of the same place fourtie shillinges, of lawfull money of Englande, to be leui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by distresse, or recouered by action, byll, playnt, or information,
<pb facs="tcp:25991:10"/> in any Court of recorde, or lordes Court, by the hygh Constables or Tythyng men aforesayde: In whiche suite, no essoigne, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, nor wager of lawe shalbe allowed or admitted to the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie defendaunt. And if the sayde hygh Constables, shalbe remisse or negligent to sue, or shal refuse to sue the sayde Collectours and euery of them within two monethes next after suche refusall, or negligence in or by the sayde Collectour: that then the sayde hygh Constables or Tithing men, shal forfayte and lose fiue poundes of lawfull money of Englande, to thufe of the poore of the same place, to be sued for, by &amp; in the name of two of the next Iustices to the sayde place or places, beyng out of Cities, Boroughes, and Townes corporate: if within, then by the Maior, Baylifes, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther head officers of the sayde Cities, Boroughes, or Townes cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate, in any Court of recorde or Lordes Court, by action of debt, byll, playnt, or information, in whiche no essoigne, protection, or wager of lawe shalbe allowed.</p>
            <p>And further be it enacted, that the sayde Collectours, and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of them, so to be chosen, as is aforesayde, shall make their iuste accompt halfe yerely of their sayde collection and gatheryng, to two Iustices of the peace, dwellyng next to the sayde abydyng place or places, not beyng within any Citie, Borough, or Towne corporate: or to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Maior, Shiriffes, or other cheefe officers, of the sayde Cities, Boroughes, or Townes corporate: and when they go out of their offices, they shall deliuer, or cause to be deliuered foorthwith vpon their accomptes, al such surplusages of their col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection &amp; gathering, as shall then remayne vndistributed, to be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sayd Iustices, Maiors, Baylifes, or other head officers, vppon the saide payne of tenne poundes. If any suche Collectour shall refuse to make his sayde accompt, or neglect the same, by the space of fourteene dayes after request to hym therfore made: then the sayde two Iustices, or one of them, to commit the sayde Collectour to the next gaole for the sayde Countie, there to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne without bayle or mainprise, tyll he haue made his sayde accompt, and immediat payment and delyuerie of al suche surplu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sages as he hath receaued.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted, that if any person or persons, beyng able to further this charitable worke, wyll obstinatly refuse to geue towardes the helpe and releefe of the sayde poore people, or doo wylfully discourage others from so charitable a deede: the
<pb facs="tcp:25991:11"/> sayde obstinate person or wylfull discourager, shall presently be brought before two Iustices of the peace, whereof one to be of the <hi>Quorum,</hi> of the same Countie, to shewe the cause of his obstinate refusal, or wylfull discouragement, and to abyde suche order ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, as the sayde iustices shall appoynt: yf he refuse so to doo, then to be committed to the next gaole for the sayde Shire, there to remayne vntyl he be contented with their sayde order, and do per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourme the same.</p>
            <p>And it is also further enacted, that if any of the sayde aged and impotent persons, not beyng so diseased, lame, or impotent, but that they may worke in some maner of worke, shalbe by the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seers of their sayde abydyng place appoynted to worke, yf they refuse, then in fourme aforesayde to be whypped and stocked for theyr fyrst refusall, and for their seconde refusall to be punished as in case of vacaboundes in the sayde firste degree of punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, and be it further enacted by thaucthoritie of this present Parliament, that three Iustices of peace, whereof one to be of the <hi>Quorum,</hi> of and with the surplussages of the sayde collections and forfaytures, (the sayde poore and impotent people satisfyed and prouided for) shall by their discretions, in such conuenient place and places within their sayde Shires as they shall thinke meete, place and settle to worke the roges and vaca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundes that shalbe disposed to worke, borne within their sayde Counties, or there abydyng for the most parte within the sayde three yeeres, there to be holden to worke by the ouersight of the sayde ouerseers, to get their lyuinges, and to lyue and to be sustay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned onely vpon their labour and trauayle.</p>
            <p>Be it also further enacted by the aucthoritie of this present Parliament, that if any beggers chylde, beyng aboue the age of fyue yeres, and vnder fourteene yeres, beyng male or female, shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be lyked of by any subiect of this Realme of honest callyng, who shalbe wyllyng to take the sayde chylde into seruice, the sayde sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect shall at the next generall sessions to be holden for the sayde Countie, by order of the Iustices there, or the moste part of them, haue the sayde chylde bounde with hym: if it be a man chylde, tyl the age of foure and twentie yeres, if it be a woman chylde, tyll the age of eyghteene yeres, If the chylde do after departe, or be taken, or be intised from the sayde maister or maistresse,
<pb facs="tcp:25991:11"/> the maister or maistresse to haue their remedie by order of the sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of labourers, as for their seruaunt, either by way of action, or otherwyse, aswel against the chylde, as agaynst the taker or intiser thereof.</p>
            <p>Be it also enacted by thaucthoritie of this present Parliament, that al the forfaytures appoynted, or to growe by this statute, (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the forfaytures of Iustices of peace) shall wholy go, and be employed to thuse of the poore aforesayde, and shalbe leuied by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stresse by the discretion of the Iustices of the same Countie or two of them, or other head officers aforesayde, and that the Iustices of peace in all Shires of Englande, shall in the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> quarter sessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons next after Easter, yerely examine the perfourmaunce, or not perfourmaunce of this statute, accordyng to the tenour thereof, as they are bounde to do the statute of labourers, and at their sayde sessions shall yerely appoynt newe collectours, and newe ouerseers for the causes aforesayde, and shall then also agree vpon newe viewes and searches of the sayde impotent people within euery their limittes for the yere folowing if neede shalbe, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at their sayde sessions, shall take order by their good discreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, for all and euery thyng and thynges, that may in any wyse further the intent of this acte.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by thaucthoritie aforesayd, that three Iustices of peace, within all the Shires of this Realme, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of one to be of the <hi>Quorum,</hi> shall haue full power by aucthoritie of this present Parliament, to heare and determine all causes, (except forfaytures of Iustices of peace) that shal come in question by reason of this present acte.</p>
            <p>Prouided also, that forasmuche as it is thought that the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitauntes of diuers Counties, Cities, and Townes within this Realme, be not able to releeue the poore, lame, and impotent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons with money, to be collected in maner and fourme aforesayde, and that it were ouer great a burden to the collectours, for to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meate, drynke, corne, or other thinges for their releefe, to be employed and bestowed in fourme aforesayd: Therefore it is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther enacted, that it shalbe lawfull to and for the Iustices of the peace, in their open sessions of the peace, or for the moste parte of them there assembled, within anye the Counties, Cities, or Townes of this Realme, where collection of money can not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently be had, as this present acte wylleth &amp; appointeth, to graunt license vnder their handes and seales, to suche, and so manye of the sayde poore and impotent, or diseased persons, or to anye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther person or persons, to be by the sayde Iustices assigned
<pb facs="tcp:25991:12"/> and allowed for the sayde poore, to aske, geather, and receaue, within suche other Towne, parishe, or parishes of the sayde Countie, as the sayd Iustices, or the most part of them, there then in their sayde Session assembled, shall especially name, appoynt, limit and assigne, the charitable deuotion, &amp; almes, at the house or houses of the inhabitantes of suche towne, parishe, or parishes, by the sayde Iustices named, appoynted, lymitted, or assigned, so that they do appoynt the sayde poore so to be releeued onely with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Townes and parishes beyng within the diuisions of the same Iustices that so shal geue suche license, or licenses: and that the inhabitantes of euery suche parishe or parishes, to the whiche suche poore or impotent persons shalbe so appoynted, as is afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayde, shalbe coacted and bounde by vertue of this acte, vnder suche payne as to the discretion of the sayde Iustices there in their session assembled, or the most part of them, shall seeme con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient, to releeue the sayde poore and impotent persons, in suche sorte, as the sayde Iustices there assembled shall appoynt.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted, that if it shal happen anye Citie or Towne corporate, to haue in it more impotent and poore folkes, not able to labour, then the sayde Towne or Citie is able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, &amp; the sayd Citie or Towne corporate is a Countie of it selfe, or scituate, or standyng in one Countie, &amp; immediatly adioynyng to another, that in those Cities, or Townes, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Maior or head offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of the sayde Citie or Towne, shall make certificate to the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stices of the Counties adioynyng to the sayd Cities or Townes, &amp; the same Iustices of the sayde adioynyng Countie or Townes, in their generall Sessions of the peace, shal geue license, and fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe the order aboue remembred, accordyng as other Iustices of the Counties in the whiche any Towne or parishe surcharged standeth, are before limitted, and aucthorized to do.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, and be it enacted by thaucthoritie afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayde, that al and euery summe &amp; summes of money, from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foorth to be collected or gathered within the Citie of London, and the liberties of the same, by vertue of this acte, shalbe payde vnto the gouernour of the Hospitall, called the Hospitall of Christes Churche, within the sayde Citie of London, for the tyme beyng, &amp; shalbe by them from tyme to tyme distributed, and bestowed, for the releefe of the poore of the same Citie, accordyng to their wyse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and discretions: any thing in this statute conteined to the contrary, notwithstandyng.</p>
            <p>Prouided also, and be it enacted by the aucthoritie aforesayde, that al and euery summe and summes of money, from henceforth
<pb facs="tcp:25991:12"/> to be collected or gathered within the citie of Couentrie, and the liberties of the same, by vertue of this act, towardes the maynte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce and releefe of the Hospitall of poore people, erected in the same citie, shalbe payd vnto suche gouernour &amp; gouernours of the said Hospital, as nowe is, or hereafter shalbe admitted &amp; appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Maior and Aldermen of the sayde citie of Couentrie, or the more part of them, for the tyme beyng, and suche gouernour and gouernours so admitted and appoynted, as is aforesayd, shal from tyme to tyme distribute and bestowe for the releefe of the poore within the sayde citie, the sayde summe or summes of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, accordyng to theyr wisdomes &amp; discretions: any thyng men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in this acte to the contrary, notwithstandyng.</p>
            <p>Prouided also, and be it enacted by the aucthoritie aforesayde, that al and euery summe and summes of money, from henceforth to be payde, collected, or gathered, within the citie of Gloucester, liberties, and limittes of the same citie, for, and towarde the vse or releefe of the poore, and al and euery other releefe which shalbe due and payable, or is to be yeelded within the sayde citie, liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or limittes, for, and towarde the releefe of the sayde poore, shalbe from tyme to tyme payde and deliuered, or otherwyse shall stande and be at the only rule, order, and disposition of the president and gouernours of the Hospitall of saint Bartho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomewe, of the foundation of our nowe moste gratious soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lady Queene Elizabeth, within the saide citie of Glouce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster for the tyme beyng, and shalbe by them from tyme to tyme distributed, and bestowed for the releefe of the poore of the sayde citie, accordyng to theyr wysdomes and discretions.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the aucthoritie aforesayde, that the Bishoppe of euery diocesse, or his Chauncelour for the tyme beyng, shall yerely visite all Hospitalles in the diocesse of suche Bishoppe, where no visitour by the founder or founders is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted, yf the founder of the sayde Hospital be then dead, and to see and take order, that the sayde Hospitalles be ordered and vsed according to the statutes and ordinaunces of the foundation thereof, and yf the founder be then lyuyng, the sayde founder to visite the same duryng his lyfe, without any the Bishoppes vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitation, and the same visitation to be at the onlye costes and charges of the visitours, and not of the Hospitalle: and that it shalbe lawfull to the Byshoppe of the diocesse for the tyme beyng, where suche Hospitall is or shalbe, or his Chauncelour, vppon complaynte, or other intelligence of iuste cause, to take accompte howe the rentes, reuenues, and profites of any suche Hospitall hath benne bestowed and spente, to call before
<pb facs="tcp:25991:13"/> hym or them at the sayde Hospital to accompt, al such person and persons as haue had the collection or receipt of any the said rents, issues, reuenues, or profites. And yf any person or persons so cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, shal, and do refuse to accompt, or entryng into accompt, shall refuse to proceede and finishe the same, or vpon the finyshyng thereof, shall refuse foorthwith to employ or aunswere to the vse of the sayde Hospitall, suche summe or summes of money, as vpon the same accompt shal appeare to be due by hym: that then euery suche person and persons so refusyng, shal forfayte and lose suche summe and summes of money, as to the sayde Byshoppe or Chauncelour, and to two Iustices of the peace next inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng to the sayde Hospitall, shalbe thought meete and conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, to whiche accomptes, the sayde Byshoppe or Chauncelour, shall cal the same two Iustices of peace.</p>
            <p>Prouided also, and be it further enacted by the aucthoritie afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayd, that no person or persons, hauyng charge of any vyage in passing from the Realme of Ireland, or from the Isle of Manne, into this Realme of Englande, do from the laste day of Iune nexte commyng, wittynglye or willynglye transporte, bryng, cary, or conueygh, or suffer to be transported, brought, caryed, or conueyghed in any shippe, picarde, vessell, boate, or boates, from and out of the sayde Realme of Irelande, or from, or out of the sayde Isle of Manne, into the Realme of Englande or Wales, or anye parte thereof, anye vacabounde, roge, or beggar, or anye suche as shalbe forced or very lyke to lyue by beggyng within the Realmes of Englande or Wales, beyng borne in the Realme of Ireland, or in the said Isle of Manne, on payne of euery such per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son or persōs, so bringing transporting, carying, or conueighing, either suffring to be brought, transported, caried, &amp; conueyghed in maner and fourme aforesayde, to forfeyte and lose for euery suche vacabounde, roge, beggar, or other person which shalbe forced, or like to liue by begging within this Realme of England or Wales, beyng transported, and set on lande in any part of Englande or of Wales, twentie shyllynges of lawfull Englishe money, to the vse of the poore of the same Parishe in whiche they were set on lande, to be leuied by the collectours of the same poore for the tyme beyng, by seasure and sellyng of any the goodes and cattels of the same person, whiche shal so bryng, transporte, carry, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueygh any suche roge, vacabounde, or beggar, or other person whiche shalbe forced, or like to liue by begging within the realme of Englande, or of Wales, to the value of the same forfeyture, and on the payne of the same vacaboundes, roges, and beggars, so set on lande, to be punished as the other vacaboundes and
<pb facs="tcp:25991:13"/> sturdie beggers, in this acte before mentioned and declared.</p>
            <p>And be it lykewyse enacted, yf any suche maniske or Irishe roge, vacabounde, or begger, ben already, or shal at any time here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after be set on lande in any part of England or of Wales, the same shalbe conueyed to the next port in or neere whiche they were landed, and from thence be transported at the common charge of the Countie where they were set on land, into those partes from whence they came, or were transported.</p>
            <p>Also be it prouided, that yf any manner of person, shal hereafter finde hym or her selfe greeued with any taxation set vpon them by vertue of this acte, it shalbe lawfull for them at the next gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Sessions of the peace, to be holden within the same shire where their taxation shalbe, to make complaint therof to the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stices of the benche, and to be eased of their excessiue charge, by the discretion of the whole benche, or the most of them. And yf any default shalbe hereafter founde in any Iustices of peace, or <hi>Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> in or about the execution of this acte: euery of the sayde Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stices, vpon proofe of their saide default by two sufficient witnes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses before the Iustices of Assise, at the next general Sessions of gaole deliuerie for the same Countie, after the same default, shall forfayte and lose fiue poundes of lawful Englishe money, the one halfe whereof to be to the vse of the sayde poore people of the same Countie, and the other halfe to the Queenes Maiestie, whiche sayde forfayture shalbe leuied by distresse, by the discretion of the sayde Iustices of Assises.</p>
            <p>And where as a great number of poore and diseased people do resorte to the Citie of Bathe, in the Countie of Sommerset, and the Towne of Buckstone, in the Countie of Derbie, for some ease and reliefe of their diseases at the bathes there, and by meanes thereof, the inhabitauntes of the same Citie of Bathe, &amp; Towne of Buckstone, are greatly ouercharged with the same poore peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to their intollerable charge: be it enacted by the aucthoritie aforesayde, that no diseased or impotent poore person, liuing on almes at any tyme after the feast of saint Bartholomewe the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle next comming, shal resort or repayre from theyr dwellyng places to the sayde Citie of Bathe, and Towne of Buckstone, or eyther of them, to the bathes there for ease of their greefe, vnlesse suche person be not only licensed so to do, by two Iustices of the peace of the Countie where suche person dooth or shal then dwel &amp; remayne: but also prouided for by the inhabitantes of such hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dredes, parishes, or places from whence they shal so be licensed to trauayle, of suche reliefe for and towardes his maintenance, as shalbe necessary for the same person, for the tyme of such his abode at the sayde Citie of Bathe and Towne of Buckstone, or eyther
<pb facs="tcp:25991:14"/> of them, and returne home agayne as shalbe limitted by the same licence, vppon payne to be reputed, punished, and vsed as vaca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundes, by the puruewe of this estatute: and that the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tauntes of the same Citie and Towne, shall not in any wyse be charged by this acte, with the findyng or reliefe of any such poore people.</p>
            <p>And for the better perfourmance of this charitable acte, it is ordeyned and established by aucthoritie aforesayde, that whereas the late kyng of famous memorie, kyng Henry the eyght, his heyres or successours, or any other person or persons, heretofore by his or theyr seueral and lawfull erections and foundations, hath or haue ordeyned or appoynted any summe or summes of money, tentes, reliefes, or commoditie to the vse of the poore, or for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payring or mendyng of hygh wayes or bridges, not beyng taken away otherwyse by acte of Parliament, whether the same be in any Cathedral Churche, Colledge, or els where, that the byshop of the diocesse, or his Chauncellour, within whiche the sayde Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedral Church, Colledge, or place is, and the Iustices of the peace of the Countie within the whiche the sayde Cathedrall Churche, Colledge, or place is, or three of them (whereof one to be of the <hi>Quorum</hi>) shall haue aucthoritie from time to time to examine howe and after what manner the sayde money, rent, reliefe, or commoditie is bestowed: and to cal to accompt the parties which do deteyne the sayde money, rentes, or reliefe, and therevpon to take suche order for the distribution of the same, as to their discre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions shall seeme most fitte and agreeable to the good intent of the founders, geuers, or graunters, and thereof to make certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate in the hygh Court of Chauncerie once in euery yeere.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, that whereas by reason of this acte, the common gaoles of euery shyre within this Realme, are like to be greatly pestered with a more number of prisoners then hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath benne, for that the sayde vacaboundes and other lewde persons before recited, shal vpon their apprehention be commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the common gaole of the same shyre where they are so taken and apprehended, and that in most shires of this Realme, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon gaoles are in suche Townes where there be a great number of poore people, more then they are wel able to susteine with their reliefe, and in some shyres the assises are kept farre distant from the place where the common gaoles are, by reason whereof the sayde prisoners are lyke to famishe for want of sustenaunce, yf they be not therefore prouided:</p>
            <p>For remedy whereof, be it therefore enacted by the aucthori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie aforesayde, that it shall and may be lawfull for the Iustices of peace of euery shyre within this Realme, at their general quarter
<pb facs="tcp:25991:14"/> sessions of the peace to be holden within the same shyres, or the most part of the saide Iustices being then present, to rate and taxe euery parishe within the sayde shyres, at such reasonable summes of money, for and towardes the reliefe of the sayde prisoners, as they shall thinke conuenient by their discretions: so that the sayd taxation and rate dooth not exceede aboue sixe pence, or eyght pence by the weeke out of euery parishe: and that the Churche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens of euery parishe within this Realme for the time being, shal euery Sunday leuie the same, and once euery quarter in the yeere pay to the hye constables, or head officers of euery Towne, Parishe, Hundred, Riding, or Wapentake within this Realme, all suche summes of money, as their parishe shalbe rated and tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for and towardes the reliefe of the saide prisoners within their saide seueral parishes: And that the sayde high Constables and head officers, and euery of them, shal pay all suche summes of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney so to them payd by the sayde Churchwardens, at euery gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall quarter Sessions to be holden within the sayd seueral shires, to suche sufficient persons dwelling nigh the sayd gaoles, as shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be appoynted by the sayde Iustices in their sayde open quarter sessions, to be there ready to receiue the sayd money so collected, as is aforesayde. And that the Collectours for the said prisoners, shal weekely distribute and pay al suche summes of money, as they and euery of them shal receiue for the reliefe of the sayd prisoners, as aforesayde, vppon payne aswell the sayde Churchwardens of euery parishe, Constables and head officers of euery Hundred, or Wapentake, as also the sayde Collectours appoynted for the col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection and contribution of the sayd prisoners, so makyng default, as aforesayde, to forfeyte fiue poundes, the one moytie thereof shalbe to the vse of the Queenes Maiestie, her heyres and succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sours, and the other moytie to the reliefe of the prisoners: any statute, lawe, custome, vse, or other thyng to the contrary in any wyse, notwithstandyng.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, that the Iustices of peace within any Countie of this Realme or Wales, shal not intromit or enter into any Citie, Borough, place, or Towne corporate, where be any Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice, or Iustices of peace, for any suche Citie, Borough, place, or Towne corporate, for the execution of any braunche, article, or sentence of this act, for, or concernyng any offence, matter, or cause growyng or arysing within the precinctes, liberties, or iurisdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of such Citie, Borough, place, or towne corporate: but that it may and shalbe lawfull to the Iustice, and Iustices of peace, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ior, Bayliffes, and other head officers of those Cities, Boroughes, places, and Townes corporate, where there be Iustice, or Iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to proceede to the execution of this acte, within the precinct
<pb facs="tcp:25991:15"/> and compasse of theyr liberties, in suche manner and fourme as the Iustices of peace in any Countie, may or ought to doo within the same Countie by vertue of this acte: any matter or thyng in this acte expressed to the contrary thereof, notwithstandyng.</p>
            <p>And that euery Iustice and Iustices of the peace, within euery suche Citie, Borough, Place, and Towne corporate, for euery of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence by them, or any of them to be committed contrary to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and meaning of this statute, shalbe punishable, and charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able as other Iustices of peace at large in the Counties, are by this acte aboue appoynted to be.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, and be it further enacted by the aucthori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie aforesayde, that yf it shal chaunce any Citie or Towne corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, to haue in it more poore folkes then the inhabitauntes ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of shalbe able to releeue, that in suche case vppon certificat there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of made, and of the number and names of the personnes with which they be so surcharged, vnto the Iustices of the peace of the Countie in whiche suche Citie or Towne corporate shall lye and be situate, at their quarter sessions of the peace, by two Iustices of peace of the sayde Countie, and the Maior or other head offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer of the same Citie or Towne corporate, the Iustices may by their discretions in the same sessions, take order, appoynt, &amp; cause the same poore folke so certified, to be prouided for, and releeued, by geuing of licence to begge, or otherwyse, in some other place or places of the sayde countie, out of suche citie or towne corporate so surcharged.</p>
            <p>Prouided alway, that this acte, or any thyng therein contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, shal not extende to the poore people, for the tyme being in the hospitall, called Saint Thomas hospitall, otherwyse called the kynges hospitall in the Borough of Southwarke, neare adioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng to the Citie of London, but that the Maior, Comminaltie, and Citizens of the sayde Citie of London for the tyme being, shal and may only haue the rule, order, and gouernment of the sayde hospitall, and of the poore people therein for the tyme beyng: any thyng in this acte to the contrary, notwithstandyng.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, that this acte, or any thyng therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned, or any aucthoritie thereby geuen, shal not in any wyse ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende to disinherite, preiudice, or hinder Iohn Dutton, of Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, in the Countie of Chester esquire, his heyres or assignes, for, touchyng, or concernyng any libertie, priuiledge, preeminence, aucthoritie, iurisdiction, or inheritaunce, whiche the sayde Iohn Dutton nowe lawefully vseth or hath, or lawfully may or ought to vse within the Countie palatine of Chester, and the Countie of the Citie of Chester, or eyther of them, by reason of any aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent chartres of any kynges of this lande, or by reason of any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription,
<pb facs="tcp:25991:15"/> or other lawful vsage or title whatsoeuer.</p>
            <p>This acte to endure for seuen yeeres, and from thence to the ende of the next Parliament then next folowyng.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <head>An acte for thexplanation <hi>of a statute made against fugitiues ouer the seas,</hi> in the .xiij. yeere of the Queenes Maiesties raigne. Chapter. vi.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HERE as in the statute</hi> agaynst fugitiues departing out of this Realme, made in the last Parliament, amongest other thynges it is ordeyned, that the offenders agaynst that estatute, shall forfayte and lose to our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne Lady the Queene, the whole profites of all their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, landes, tenementes, and hereditamentes, during their liues: sythens whiche tyme some doubt and question vpon the sayde woordes hath rysen, and ben mooued, Whether her Maiestie, her heyres and successours, may let and set the same landes, or make grauntes by coppies of court roule thereof, and vsuall wood sales, or els shall only take the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie profites as they ryse, as <hi>vesturam terre,</hi> &amp; not otherwyse: And where as in the saide estatute, one braunche or clause is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned for the makyng voyde of fraudulent conueyaunces by the sayde fugitiues of their landes and goodes, made to thintent and vpon priuie confidence, that the profits may be employed, as they shoulde limit and agree: vpon the woordes of which clause, some doubt and question hath also risen, and ben mooued, Whether the conueyaunce (to thintent aforesayde) made by suche fugitiues as depart out of the Realme hauing licence, and do not returne into this Realme accordyng to their licence, and intent of the said esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, shalbe within the prouision of the said estatute, vnlesse their determination of not returnyng accordyng to their licence, be prooued to be before the makyng of the sayde fraudulent conuey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce, as a thing material before the making of the saide conuey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce, or whether the same determination of not returnyng ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng
<pb facs="tcp:25991:16"/> to the sayde licence, be not so materiall, but that the same shall by the subsequent acte, (that is to say) by the not returnyng of the saide partie accordyng to the sayde licence, be sufficiently prooued, without any further matter.</p>
            <p>For auoydyng of whiche doubtes: be it declared, and expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and ordeyned by aucthoritie of this Parliament, that during so long tyme as her Maiestie, her heyres or successours, shalbe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled to haue the sayde profites by vertue of the sayde estatute, she and they may let and sette, and make grauntes by coppy of Court roule, and vsual wood sales, and other thynges, to all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes and purposes, as a tenant <hi>pour terme dauter vie</hi> lawfully may do.</p>
            <p>And further, that the sayde determination, whiche is but a secrete thought of the fugitiue, whatsoeuer his woordes or speach be, is not materiall, but that the acte and deede subsequent, viz. the not returnyng of euery suche fugitiue accordyng to this li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, and not hauing suche let or excuse, as by the sayde statute is alowed (without any further matter) was, is, and shalbe ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and deemed a sufficient proofe of the precedent determinatiō of the same partie not to returne accordyng to his licence: any thyng to the contrary hereof in any wyse, notwithstandyng.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the aucthoritie aforesayde, that all suche rentes, reuenues, issues, profites, and other thynges, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready be commen or growen, or hereafter shall come or growe to the Queenes Maiestie, for any the causes of forfaiture mentioned or expressed in the saide former acte and statute, or declared by this acte, shalbe answeared yeerely vnto the Queenes Maiestie in the Court of Exchequer, and shalbe in the order, surueye, and rule of the same Court: and that the Treasourer, Chauncelour, and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons of the sayde Court, or the more part of them for the tyme be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, whereof the Treasourer, or Chauncelour to be one, shall and may doo, and cause to be donne, all and euery suche acte and thyng, as they shal thinke meete and conuenient to be had, made, or donne, for the demising, custody, receiuing, orderyng, and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter answearing to her Maiesties commoditie and profite, of all such rentes, reuenues issues, profites, and other thynges as now be commen or growen, or hereafter shall come or growe to her Maiestie, for any the causes of forfaiture aforesayde, accordyng to the true intent and meanyng of the sayde former acte, and of this present statute of explanation and declaration.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, and be it further enacted by the aucthoritie aforesayde, that al landes, tenementes, rentes, reuertions, serui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, &amp; leasses, being at this time parcel of the possessiōs of the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie of Lancaster, or deriued out of the same, whereunto, or to the
<pb facs="tcp:25991:16"/> profites wherof, the Queenes Maiestie, her heyres or successours in any wyse is, or hereafter shalbe entituled, eyther by aucthoritie of the sayde former estatute of fugitiues, or by this estatute, shalbe from hencefoorth within the suruey, dimising, and order of the Court of the saide Duchie of Lancaster, in such maner &amp; fourme, as other the premises be assigned or appoynted by aucthoritie of this acte, or by the sayde former acte, to be in the suruey, dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing, and order of the sayde Court of Exchequer: and that the transcripte of all offices and inquisitions concernyng the premis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses to be within the suruey, dimising, and order of the sayde Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie of Lancaster, shalbe certified and recorded in the sayde Court of the Duchie of Lancaster: any thing eyther in the saide former acte, or in this acte to the contrary, notwithstandyng.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <head>An act against the deceiptes <hi>of vnder Collectours of the tenthes and</hi> sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidies of the Cleargie. Chapter. vij.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR auoydyng and redresse</hi> of great deceiptes donne to the Queenes Maiestie, and to the Prelates and Cleargie of this Realme, by vnder Collectours of the tenthes and subsidies of the Cleargie, appointed by and vnder the Archbyshops and Byshops of this Realme, and Deanes and Chapters <hi>(Sede vacante:)</hi> Be it enacted, that the statute made in the .xiii. yeere of her Maiesties raigne, to make the landes, tenementes, goodes, and catayles of Tellers, Receiuers. &amp;c. to be liable to the payment of their debtes, shal to al intentes and purposes, as amply &amp; largely extende, and be construed to extende to all suche vnder Collectours of tenthes and subsidies of the Cleargie, and to their landes, tenementes, and hereditamentes, goodes, and cattayles, for satisfiyng of suche money as they haue collected, or shall collect of the sayde tenthes and subsidies, to the vse of the Queenes Maiestie, her heyres or successours, (of what yeerely summe so euer the charge of their collection is, or shalbe) in lyke fourme as it dooth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to the Tellers, Receiuers, and other personnes accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunt, whom the sayde acte specially and expressely concerneth,
<pb facs="tcp:25991:17"/> and in as ample wyse, as yf suche vnder Collectours were imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly accomptaunt to the Queenes Maiestie, her heyres or suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessours: any prouision in the said statute, or other matter what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer to the contrary, notwithstandyng.</p>
            <p>And that euery such vnder Collectour, shal vpon processe to be awarded out of the court of Exchequer, be chargeable to accompt for his receipt of suche tenthes and subsidies, as any Receiuer im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly accomptaunt to her Maiestie, is or ought to be: and that euery Archbyshoppe and Byshop, and Deane and Chapter <hi>(Sede vacante)</hi> to whose charge the collection of suche tenthes or subsidies dooth, or shall apparteyne, shalbe discharged of so much of the sayd tenthes &amp; subsidies, as shalbe satisfied to the Queenes Maiestie, her heyres or successours, of or by the landes, tenemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, hereditamentes, goodes or cattayles, of suche vnder Collec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour or his heyres, without any other warraunt whatsoeuer, in that behalfe to be obteyned.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>An acte for the auoydyng</hi> of recoueries suffered by collusion by tenauntes for terme of life, and suche others. <hi>Chapter. viij.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HERE diuers persons</hi> being seised, or that had ben seised of landes, tenementes, and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditamentes, as tenauntes by the curtesie of Englande, tenauntes in tayle after possibilitie of issue extincte, or otherwyse, onlye for terme of life or liues, or of estates determinable vppon life or liues, haue heretofore permitted and suffered other persons by agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or couine betweene them had, to recouer the same landes and tenementes, and other here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditaments, against the same particuler tenaunts, in the Queenes Maiesties Court, or haue permitted and suffered them selues to be vouched by other persons, by agreement or couine betweene them had, in recoueries suffered of the same landes, tenementes, and other hereditamentes, in the Queenes Maiesties Court, to the great preiudice of those to whom the reuertion or remaynder thereof hath apparteyned, or ought to apparteyne.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:25991:17"/>
            <p>For remedy whereof, be it enacted by the Queenes most excellent Maiestie, with the assent of the lordes Spiritual and Temporal, and the Commons in this present Parliament assembled, and by aucthoritie of the same, that all suche recoueries hereafter to be had or prosecuted by agreement of the parties, or by couine, as is aforesayde, agaynst any suche particuler tenaunt of any landes, tenementes, or hereditamentes, whereof the same particuler te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunt is, or hereafter shalbe seised of any suche particuler estate, as is aforesayde, or agaynst any other with voucher ouer of any suche particuler tenaunt, or of any hauyng, or that had ryght or title to any suche particuler estate or tenauncie, as is aforesayde, shall from hencefoorth, as agaynst suche person or personnes to whom any reuertion or remaynder thereof, by force of any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyaunce or deuice before that tyme had or made, shall, ought, or lawfully may apparteyne, and agaynst their heyres and suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessours, be clearely and vtterly voyde and of none effect: any law or vsage heretofore had to the contrary thereof, in any wyse not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstandyng.</p>
            <p>Prouided alway, that this acte, nor any thing therein contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, shal extende, or be preiudiciall to any person or persons, that shal hereafter by good title recouer any landes, tenementes, or hereditaments, without fraud or couine, by reason of any former right, or title: but that al and euery suche recouerie, and recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, so to be had or prosecuted vpon former rightes or titles, shall stande and be in like force, strength, and effect, as they were before the making of this acte: any thyng herein conteyned to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, in any wyse notwithstandyng.</p>
            <p>Prouided also, that all and euery suche recouerie and recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, to be had or prosecuted of any landes, tenementes, or heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamentes, as aforesayde, by the assent and agreement of any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son or persons, to whom any reuertion or remaynder thereof then shal or ought to apparteyne (so that the same assent &amp; agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment do appeare of recorde in any court of our Soueraigne La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy the Queenes Maiestie, her heyres or successours) shall stande and be in lyke force, strength, and of like effect, agaynst suche per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son and persons that shall so assent and agree, their heyres and successours, as they were before the makyng of this acte: any thyng herein conteyned to the contrary, in any wyse notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standyng.</p>
            <p>Be it further enacted by the aucthoritie aforesaid, that one acte made in the xxxii. yeere of our late Soueraigne Lorde king Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the eyght, entituled, An acte for the auoyding of recoueries by collusions by tenauntes for terme of lyfe, shalbe from the first day of Iuly next ensuing repealed, and shall no longer stande in force.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:25991:18"/>
            <head>
               <hi>An acte declaring that the</hi> tenaunt and defendaunt, may haue a <hi>tales de circumstantibus,</hi> aswell as the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundant or plaintife. <hi>Chapter. ix.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR the auoydyng of great and chargeable delayes oftentymes happenyng vnto te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nauntes and defendauntes: be it enacted, that in all cases whereas the partie plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tife or demaundant by any statute hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore made, may haue vppon his or their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest made vnto the Iustices of <hi>Nisi prius,</hi> within this Realme of Englande, or to the Iustices of Eyre, or of assises, of the twelue shyres of Wales, and of the counties palatines of Lancaster, Chester, and Durham, a <hi>tales de circumstantibus,</hi> that in al and euery such case and cases, the partie and parties, tenauntes, actours, auowauntes, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendauntes (yf the plaintiefes or demaundantes shall vppon the calling of the principal pannel or Iurie, forbeare or refuse to pray the same) shall and may vpon his or their request or desyre, haue vpon the same recorde, and by the same Iustices, the tales or ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesses vnto them graunted, in like manner, fourme, and degree, to all respectes and purposes, as the plaintiefe or demaundant in any suite or action, may haue the same by any statute or ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce heretofore made, or set foorth, and the rather for the speedy tryal of the issue and issues ioyned, or hereafter to be ioyned in any plee, suite, or action: any lawe, custome, or vsage heretofore vsed to the contrary thereof in any wyse, notwithstandyng.</p>
            <p>Prouided also, and be it further enacted by the aucthoritie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresayde, that in all populer actions, informations, billes, or suites, commenced or had, or hereafter to be commenced or had in any the Queenes Maiesties courtes of recorde, vpon any penall lawes or statutes, wherein any personne dooth, or shall sue, or prosecute, or infourme, aswell for the Queenes Maiestie, her heyres and successours, as for hym selfe, whereupon issue is or shalbe ioyned to be tryed by the Countrey: that therein the partie defendaunt, or defendauntes, shalbe admitted to pray and haue a <hi>tales de circumstantibus,</hi> as in other cases aforesayde.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:25991:18"/>
            <head>¶ An Acte to refourme the <hi>excessiue length of karsies.</hi> Chapter. x.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HERE as within this</hi> Realme of Englande, Karsies, called ordinarie karsies, haue not, nor doo not vsually contayne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue seuenteene yardes, and the finer sort, called sorting karsies, not aboue eyghteene yardes, and according to the proportion of the sayde lengthes, the weyght hath ben limitted by the statutes now remaynyng in force for true ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng of woollen karsies: and where the Queenes Maiestie hath ben, is, and ought to be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sweared of her Maiesties customes and subsidies of the sayde kar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies, accordyng to the number of peeces, or whole karsies, and not accordyng to the quantitie or number of yardes, in euery of the sayde karsies conteyned: and where certaine marchaunt stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and others, vsing the trade of transporting karsies by way of marchaundize beyonde the seas, haue of late deuised and procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to haue karsies made of much greater lengthes, as of xxv. and xxvi. yardes and more, and intende, as it may be wel geathered, to haue them made of greater length from tyme to time, by whiche policie they doo not only deceiue the Queenes Maiestie of one thirde part of her customes and subsidies due for the same karsies, for that euery two karsies nowe paying custome but for two kar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies, do by the sayde meane contayne more then three karsies, that were wont to yeelde custome for three karsies: but also the poore Artificers, Weauers, and other woorkemen, occupying making of the sayde karsies, are sicle or nothyng more consydered in theyr wages for making of the sayde long karsies: Moreouer, the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chauntes of Englande vsing the trade of bying the sayde vsuall ordinarie sortes, or others, are easely eaten vp and vndonne by the sayde straungers, for that the sayde straungers conueying by deceipte so muche of her Maiesties custome, are able by selling beyonde the seas vnder the Englishe marchauntes price, to driue all the Englishe marchauntes to losse, and Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishe subiectes makers of ordinarie karsies, are by the sayde sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyle aduauntage dryuen from theyr trade, and lykely to be
<pb facs="tcp:25991:19"/> shortly enforced to chaunge their Loumes, Misles, and other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strumentes, for that no other sort of karsies, in respect of the gayne in deceiuing her Maiestie, are likely to be vsually bought, which newe deuise is to the great defraudyng of her Maiestie, to the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing of her subiectes, the Englishe marchauntes, and of the Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiers vsing the makyng of karsies, and of an infinite number of poore families susteyned by woorkemanship about the same.</p>
            <p>Be it therefore enacted by the Queenes highnesse, the Lordes Spirituall and Temporall, and the Commons in this present Parliament assembled, that from and after the feast of Saint Bartholomewe the Apostle next ensuing, it shal not be lawfull for any person or persons, vsing, or that shall vse the trade of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng of karsies, to make or cause to be made any karsies of the sorte called ordinarie karsies, or any sortyng karsies, or any other karsies, by what name or names so euer they be called, aboue the length of eyghteene yardes at the moste, to be measured by yarde and ynche, beyng redy made: but that all karsies shalbe made of the sayde vsuall lengthes, and accordyng to the proportion of weyght limitted by the statute in that behalfe made and proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the fourth and fyfth yeeres of the raignes of the late kyng Philip and Queene Marie, vppon payne that euery person or persons, that shal make, or cause to be made, any suche karsie or karsies of more or greater length then eyghteene yardes, shall forfayte for euery suche karsie .xl. s. the one moytie whereof shalbe to the Queenes Maiestie, her heyres and successours, and the other moytie to hym or them that wyl sue for the same, by byll, plaint, or information, in any of the Queenes Maiesties Courtes of Recorde, wherein no essoigne, protection, or wager of lawe, for the defendaunt shalbe admitted or allowed.</p>
            <p>Prouided, that yf any karsie or karsies beyng purposely made to contayne eyghteene yardes in length, and no more, shall by occasion happen to contayne aboue eyghteene yardes, and being vnder nineteene yardes in length, that the maker or makers of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny suche karsie or karseies, shall not incurre the penaltie aboue conteyned, any thing before mentioned to the contrary, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standyng.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:25991:19"/>
            <head>❧ <hi>An Acte for the</hi> conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuation, explanation, perfiting, and enlarging of diuers statutes. <hi>Chapter. xj.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here in the parliament hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> vppon prorogation at West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster the fourth day of Februa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, in the .xxiiii. yere of the raigne of the late kyng Henry the eyght, one acte was there made, entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, An acte to continue, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new the act made agaynst kylling of Calues: and one other acte en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, An acte agaynst kyllyng of young beastes, called waynlings. And where in the session of a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament ended at Westminster in the first day of Februarie, in the fourth yere of the raigne of our late soueraigne Lorde kyng Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde the sixth, one acte was made concernyng the buying and sellyng of rother beastes: and also one other acte was then and there lykewyse made, entituled, An acte for the buying and sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng of butter and cheese. And where also an acte was made in the first session of the Parliament, holden in the fyfth yere of the Queenes Maiesties raigne, entituled, An acte for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce and encrease of Tyllage. And where also in the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment begunne at Westminster in the .xxiii. day of Ianuary in the firste yere of the raigne of the Queenes Maiestie that nowe is, and there continued by prorogation vntyll the dissolution there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, one acte was then and there made, entituled, An acte for the preseruation of spawne and frye of fyshe. And where also in the first session of the Parliament begunne and holden at Westminster, in the fyfth yere of the raigne of our soueraigne Lady the Queenes Maiestie that nowe is, and from thence con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued by prorogation vntyll the dissolution thereof, one acte
<pb facs="tcp:25991:20"/> was then and there made, entituled, An acte for the auoydyng of diuers forrayne wares, made by handycraftes men beyond the seas: and one other acte, entituled, An acte for the punishment of suche persons as shoulde procure or commit any wylfull periurie, whiche actes were limited to endure to thende of the next Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament. And where also in the last session of the same Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment holden by prorogation at Westminster, in the eyght yere of the raigne of the Queenes most excellent Maiestie that nowe is, one acte was then and there made, entituled, An acte for Bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers, and the prices of bowes, and was made to continue to thend of the first session of the next Parliament: and also one other acte was then made, entituled, An acte for the preseruation of grayne: All whiche seuerall actes and statutes were made to continue, but for certayne tymes: and all whiche actes made in the sayde fourth yere of kyng Edwarde the sixth, and in the sayd first, fyfth, and eyght yeres of the Queenes Maiesties raigne, were at the last Parliament holden at Westminster the seconde day of Apryll, in the thirteenth yeere of the raigne of our sayd soueraigne Lady the Queenes Maiestie, made to continue and stande in force vnto thende of the next Parliament then next folowyng. And where also in the Parliament begunne and holden at Westminster the seconde day of Apryll, in the thirteenth yere of the raigne of our sayde soueraigne Lady the Queene, one acte and statute was then and there made, for the auoydyng and abolishing of faigned, couenous, and fraudulent feoffamentes, gyftes, grauntes, aliena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, conueyaunces, bondes, suites, iudgementes, and executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, entituled, An acte agaynst fraudulent deedes, gyftes, grauntes, alienations, &amp;c. whiche acte and statute was then made to endure vnto thende of the first session of the next Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, as by the sayde acte more playnely wyll appeare. And where also in the saide Parliament begunne and holden at West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster the sayde seconde day of Apryll, there was also one other acte and statute made for the auoydyng of some leasses in certayne cases to be made of Ecclesiasticall promotions with cure, entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, An acte touchyng leasses of benefices, and other Ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call lyuinges with cure, whiche acte was lykewyse made to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue to thende of the next Parliament. And where also there was one other acte and statute made in the sayde Parliament, begunne and holden at Westminster the sayde seconde daye of Apryll, in the sayde thirteenth yeere, entituled, An acte that
<pb facs="tcp:25991:20"/> purueyours may take grayne, corne, or victualles within fiue miles of Cambridge and Oxforde in certayne cases, whiche acte was made lykewyse to continue to the last day of the next Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</p>
            <p>And where in the statute made in the thirteenth yeere of the Queenes Maiesties raigne, entituled, An acte for the reuiuyng and continuaunce of certayne statutes, is conteyned one prouiso, that the sayde acte concernyng the auoydyng of forren wares made by handycraftes men beyonde the seas, or any clause, arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, or meanyng therein conteyned, shoulde not in any wyse ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende or be preiudicial to any entercourse, or treatise of any enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course then standyng in force, had, or made betweene the proge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitours of the Queenes Maiestie, or her hyghnesse, and any others. Nowe for good consyderations, and specially that straun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers may not be at libertie, and the Queenes Maiesties naturall subiectes restrained: be it enacted that the sayde prouiso, and euery clause, article, and matter therein conteyned, shall from hencefoorth be repelled, and vtterly voyde.</p>
            <p>Prouided also, and be it enacted, that these woordes (so soone as it, or any part thereof, shall come to any possession or vse aboue forbidden, or) whiche woordes are conteyned in the sayde statute made in the sayde thirteenth yeere, touchyng leasses of benefices, and other ecclesiasticall liuinges with cure, shall not be reuiued by this acte, but remaine discontinued, and shal from hencefoorth be omitted out of the sayde acte, any thyng in the sayde acte, or in this acte to the contrary, notwithstandyng.</p>
            <p>And where sundry euyll disposed persons, haue defrauded the true meanyng of the sayde last mentioned statute, made in the sayde xiii. yeere, by bondes and couenauntes of suffering other persons to enioy ecclesiasticall liuinges, and the fruites thereof, for that suche bondes and couenauntes are not in lawe taken to be leasses, although in deede they amount to as muche: be it therefore enacted, that all bondes, contractes, promises, and coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nauntes, hereafter to be made for suffering or permitting any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to enioy any benefice, or ecclesiasticall promotion with cure, or to take profites or fruites thereof, other then such bondes and couenauntes, as shalbe made for assuraunce of any lease hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore made, shalbe to all intentes and purposes adiudged of suche force and validitie, and not otherwyse, as leasses by the same per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons made of suche benefices and ecclesiasticall promotions with cure.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:25991:21"/>
            <p>And be it further declared and enacted, that all leasses, bondes, promises, and couenauntes of and concernyng benefices and ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiasticall liuinges with cure, to be made by any curate, shalbe of no other, nor better force, validitie, or continuaunce, then yf the same had ben made by the beneficed person him self, that dimised, or shall dimise the same to any suche Curate.</p>
            <p>And where in one other acte made in the said thirteenth yeere, entituled, An acte agaynst fraudulent gyftes, to the intent to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feate dilapidations of ecclesiasticall liuinges, and for leasses to be graunted by Collegiat Churches, there is one braunch to auoyde certayne leasses to be made by maisters and fellowes of Colled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, Deanes and Chapters of Cathedral or Collegiat Churches, maisters or gardians of any Hospitall, or by any Parson, Vicar, or any other hauyng any spirituall or ecclesiasticall liuing: be it enacted, that the sayde braunche, nor any thing therein contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, shall not extende to any graunt, assuraunce, or lease of any houses belongyng to any the persons or bodyes politique or cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate aforesayde, nor to any groundes to suche houses appartey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng, whiche houses be situate in any Citie, Borough, Towne corporate, or market Towne, or the suburbes of any of them, but that al such houses and groundes may be graunted, dimised, and assured, as by the lawes of this Realme, and the seuerall statutes of the sayde Colledges, Cathedrall Churches and Hospitalles, they lawefully myght haue benne before the makyng of the sayd statute, or lawfully myght be, yf the sayde statute were not, so al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way that suche house be not the Capitall or dwellyng house vsed for the habitation of the persons abouesayde, nor haue grounde to the same belongyng, aboue the quantitie of tenne acres, any thyng in the sayde acte to the contrary, notwithstandyng.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted, that all summes of money hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be recouered, for, or in name of dilapidations, by sentence, composition, or otherwyse, shall within two yeeres after suche receipt, be truely imployed vpon the buyldynges &amp; reparations, in respect whereof such money for dilapidations shalbe payde, on paine that euery person so receiuing, and not imploying as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayd, shal forfaite double as muche, as so shal be by hym receiued, and not imployed, the whiche forfaiture shalbe to the vse of the Queenes Maiestie, her heyres and successours.</p>
            <p>Prouided alway and be it enacted, that no lease shalbe permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be made by force of this acte in reuersion, nor without reser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb facs="tcp:25991:21"/> the accustomed yeerely rent at the least, nor without char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the lessee with the reparations, nor for longer terme then fourtie yeeres at the most: nor any houses shalbe permitted to be aliened, vnlesse that in recompence thereof, there shalbe afore, with, or presently after such alienation, good, lawful, &amp; sufficient assuraunce made in fee simple absolutely to such Colledges, hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, bodyes politike or corporate, and their successours, of landes of as good value, and of as great yeerely value at the least, as so shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be aliened: any statute to the contrary, notwithstandyng.</p>
            <p>And forasmuche as all the same seuerall actes and statutes, and euery of them, do seeme good, beneficial, and needefull to be further continued for the weale and profite of this Realme: be it therefore nowe enacted by the Queenes most excellent Maiestie, with the assent of the Lordes Spirituall and Temporall, and the Commons in this present Parliament assembled, and by the auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of the same, that the same seuerall actes and statutes, and euery of them, and all and euery article, clause, and sentences in them and euery of them conteyned, shall continue, be, and endure in full force and effect, vntyl the ende of the next Parliament.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>An acte for the repeale of</hi> a statute made Anno, viij. of the Queenes Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties raigne, touching the towne of Shrewesburie. <hi>Chapter. xij.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HERE at the Parliament hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> at Westminster the last day of Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, in the eyght yeere of the raigne of our Soueraigne Lady the Queenes most excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Maiestie, there was an acte made, enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, An acte touchyng Drapers, Cotte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, &amp; Frizers, in the Towne of Shrewes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burie, in the Countie of Salop: and in the
<pb facs="tcp:25991:22"/> same acte there is conteyned matter then supposed for the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite of the said Towne of Shrewesburie, in aduauncing the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration of Drapers, Cottoners, and Frizers of the sayd Towne. And it was thereby enacted, that from and after the feast of Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster then next ensuing, no maner person or persons whatsoeuer, inhabiting and dwelling within the saide Towne of Shrewes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burie, or the liberties or franchises of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same Towne, (other then suche as then had, or then after shoulde serue as apprentise in the occupation or science of Drapers, or then had benne, or thereafter shoulde be free of the sayde science or mysterie) should occupie, vse, exercise, or frequent the said trade, arte, mysterie, or science of buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the said welsh cloth, or lining, cottens, fryzes, or plaines: nor haue any factour or dooer for him or them in the same, nor by any colour, engin, or fraude, buye any of the said fryzes, lininges, cottons, and plaines, vpon paine that euery person &amp; persons in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habiting, as is aforesayde, and occupying, vsing, or exercising the said trade, arte, mysterie, occupation, or science of buying of welsh clothes and lininges. &amp;c. and not aucthorised by the acte, shoulde lose &amp; forfaite for euery peece of the said clothes bought .vi. s. viii. d</p>
            <p>And where sithence the makyng of the sayde acte, experience hath plainely taught in the sayde Towne, that the sayd acte hath not only not brought the good effect that then was hoped and surmised, but also hath ben, and nowe is lykely, to be the very greatest cause of the impouerishing and vndooing of the poore ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificers and other, at whose suite the saide acte was procured, for that there be nowe sithence the makyng of the sayd statute, much fewer persons to set them a woorke then before: and by restray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng all other inhabitours of the sayd Towne of Shrewesbury, from the former lawfull trade euer heretofore vsed of buying of welshe clothes, fryzes, cottons, lyninges, and playnes (leauyng the same neuerthelesse free for all the subiectes of Englande without any restraynt, sauing for the sayde inhabitauntes of the Towne of Shrewesbury, and the liberties and franchises of the same Towne only) hath ben the euident occasion of great decay, not only to the saide Towne, and the liberties and franchises of the same, but also to a great and infinite number of poore peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in Northwales, that is to say, in the Counties of Mountgo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mery, Denbigh, Merionneth, and also the Towne of Oswester, and the greatest part of the Countrey there aboutes, where the sayde Welshe clothes, fryzes, cottons, lyninges, and playnes are
<pb facs="tcp:25991:22"/> made and solde, whiche were woont to be maynteyned and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieued by trade of makyng or woorkyng of the sayde fryzes, cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons, &amp;c. contrary to the expectation that then was wrongfully conceiued.</p>
            <p>Be it therfore, at the humble suite of the inhabitauntes of the sayde Towne, and also of the sayde artificers for whose benefite the sayde acte was supposed to be prouided, enacted, that the saide acte, and all the matter in the sayde acte conteyned, shall from hencefoorth be repealed and made voyde: any thyng in the sayde acte to the contrary notwithstandyng.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, that so muche of the sayde statute of the eyght yeere of our Soueraigne Ladye the Queenes Maiestie that nowe is, and euery article and braunche therein conteyned, as toucheth the present and ready payment of money to Shere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Cottoners, and Frizers, for their worke, &amp; also as toucheth the restraint of suche as shall, or doo occupie or vse the trade of buying of frizes, cottons, or playnes, from the vse or exercise of the facultie of fryzing or cottoning, shall stande and be in force: any thing in this statute to the contrary, notwithstandyng.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="chapter">
            <head>An Acte for the annexing of Hexham and Hexhamshire to the <hi>Countie of Northumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande.</hi> Chapter. xiij.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HERE for the space of diuers</hi> yeres nowe past, the Queene her high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and her most noble and dearely beloued father king Henry the eyght, kyng Edwarde the sixth her highnesse brother, Queene Marie her late sister, as in the right of the imperiall crowne of this Realme of Englande, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of one exchaunge had, and passed betweene the sayd late kyng Henry the
<pb facs="tcp:25991:23"/> eyght, and the late reuerend father Robert Archebishop of Yorke, in the yere of the most noble raigne of the sayd late king Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, haue ben, and her maiestie yet is seased of and in the fraunchise and libertie of Hexham and Hexamshire, lying within the body and mydle of the Countie of Northumberlande, whiche sayde li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie &amp; territorie, when it was in the handes of the sayde Arche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishop, was commonly tearmed &amp; named a Countie Palentyne, where in ryght or proofe there was none suche, yet by reason of that errour, euer since, and yet, there hath ben, and are diuers opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, besides some question and doubtes, whether the sayd liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and territorie of Hexham and Hexhamshire, should and ought to be part of the sayde Countie of Northumberland, or otherwyse exempted: and whether the dwellers &amp; inhabitours there, shoulde and ought to be iustifiable, and aunswere to iustice as other of the sayde Countie of Northumberland are, and ought, or not: and the like question and doubt yet is, and remaineth. By reason wherof, not onely Plees of the Crowne, and suites betwixt partie &amp; partie haue suffered continuall stayes, lets, and also haue had no ende of tryall, and besides, the most &amp; greatest offendours to the crowne &amp; their Countrey, haue, &amp; dayly runne thither as vnto a sanctuarie, vpon hope and trust of refuge and safegarde thereby, to the great comfort and encouragement of many, the vilest &amp; worste subiectes and offendours in all the North parties, and to the great offence of the almightie &amp; most manifest hinderaunce of good execution of lawes and iustice. In and for due remedie and redresse of suche great enormities &amp; apparante mischieues, may it therefore please the queene her Maiestie, that by her highnesse, the lordes spiritual and temporal, &amp; the commons in this present hygh court of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament nowe assembled, that it may be enacted, manifested, and declared by aucthoritie of the same, that the sayd territorie, fraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chise, and libertie of Hexham and Hexhamshire, with the liberties of the same, may be, is, and shalbe from hencefoorth taken to be within, and part, parcell and member of the sayd Countie of Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thumberlande. And that as wel the Plees of the Crowne, as also al suites betwixt partie and partie, may proceede, &amp; haue their due ende and tryall within the sayde Countie of Northumberland, by and before the Shirife and Coroners of the sayde Shire, and also before the Iustices of peace, Iustices of gaole deliuerie, Iustices of assise, <hi>Nisi prius,</hi> Oyer and determiner, and other officers, and eche and euery of them, as the case shall require, and take effectes
<pb facs="tcp:25991:23"/> as any of the like haue ben, or ought to be, which haue hapned, or shall hereafter happen within the sayd Countie of Northumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande: and that from hencefoorth the Shirife and other officers of the Countie of Northumberland, for the time being, may haue full power and aucthoritie to execute his or their office, and al pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesses to him or them directed within Hexham and Hexhamshire, and liberties of the same, in as ample &amp; large maner, as he or they may, should, or ought to do, within any other part of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> said Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Northumberlande, any graunt, priuilege, custome, vsage, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, or thing els whatsoeuer heretofore made, claymed, vsed, had, put in vre or execution, or enioyed, to the contrarie notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing. Sauing to the Bayliffe of the liberties, or other offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of the sayde Towne of Hexham and Hexhamshire, or the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties therof, al liberties and priuileges for executing of processe, returne of wryttes, and otherwyse, as they or any of them of right ought to haue before the makyng of this acte.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="list_of_Acts_of_Parliament">
            <head>A Table of certayne actes passed, Anno. xiiij. Reginae Elizabethe, and not printed.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>N Acte for the assuraunce of giftes, graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. &amp;c. made, and to be made for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe of the poore in Hospitales. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>An act for the assurance of certaine lands, and tenementes, accordyng to the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng of syr Thomas and syr William Woodhouse, Knightes, for the benefite of certayne infantes.</p>
            <p>An Act for the cōtinuaunce of the innyng of Plumsted marsh, in the Countie of Kent, beyng surrounded.</p>
            <p>An Acte for the better &amp; further assuraunce of certayne landes, and tenementes, to the mayntenaunce of the free Grammer scoole of Tunbridge, in the Countie of Kent.</p>
            <closer>God saue the Queene.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:25991:24"/>
            <p>❧ Imprinted at London in <hi>Powles Churchyarde by Richarde Iugge,</hi> Printer to the Queenes Maiestie.</p>
            <p>Cum priuilegio Regiae Maiestatis.</p>
            <figure>
               <p>LOVE KEPYTH THE LAWE OBEYETH THE KYNGE, AND IS GOOD TO THE COMMEN WELTHE</p>
               <p>PRO LEGE REGE, ET GREGE</p>
               <p>PRVDENCIA IVSTICIA</p>
            </figure>
            <pb facs="tcp:25991:24"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>